Hello and welcome to a hardware layout walk
through for computer architecture for everybody.
This walk through is going to design a CMOS
NOR gate circuit which is actually one of the
assignments but I'm going to use this as uh to
show you how the tool works. So let's go across
the top. We have a button to add a switch. So
that's how we give inputs. We have a button
to add a probe. That's how we measure outputs.
So, you click the probe button and then you go
into the and you click where the probe is at. And
you'll notice that the switch has a little output
dot and the probe has an input and an output dot.
Then you can put some transistors down. You can
put NMOS transistors down. And I always the way I
remember NMOS transistors is NMOS transistors are
like the original ones that uh that basically
when their input is one they're conducting and
when their input is zero they're not conducting.
And then you have a PMOS transistor where it's
the opposite. So let me just connect this little
input 5V input to the inputs of the NMOS that I
put at the the bottom and the PMOS that I put at
the top. And so you'll see that when I'm pointing
five volts to the the NMOS, it's on and the PMOS
is off. And then when I flip it to zero volts,
the PMOS is on and the NMOS is off. Okay. So,
so you can place all three of these components
and you can draw wires by basically dragging
them to the uh the inputs. And then you have
uh the ability to move things around, right? You
can move them around by pressing the little hand
and then dragging and moving them around. You
have a little trash can icon that allows you to
get rid of something. You can clear it all. You
can actually load and store circuits. So I can
save this one as test one and then you can load it
back up. And so that way you can work on a circuit
and then reload it. Now this is the same circuit
but this way you can walk away from your computer.
Now, this actually stores the circuits in local
storage on your browser, not in the server. So,
the same browser will have your circuits. Um,
and let's just go ahead and delete that circuit.
Delete test one. Okay. Um, and you won't see this
instructor button, but then here's the assignment
button. So, if you click on the assignment
button, it tells you what your assignment is.
And it also lets you see the in this case because
it's an OR gate, you can see the truth table. And
again remember nor is not or. So you take as you
know if either of them are true then or would be
true but really it's not or so they're false. So
the only time that this output is supposed to be
high is when both A and B are low. So let's also
take a look at the reference image and this is
straight from the lecture. So we have our voltage
at the top and then we have two PMOS transistors
in series to the common output and then we have
two NMOS's in parallel. And part of this is is
remember that NMOS's conduct when they're a one.
So if A is a one or B is a one, ground is going to
conduct out. And the only way a one or a positive
is going to conduct out is if A and B are both
zero. Okay. So that is the definition of NAND. And
so I tend to to draw these and most people tend to
draw these with the POMS's near the top and the
NMOS's near the bottom. In the real world they
get laid out much more intricately, but that's
okay. Right now we're kind of pretending that
we have NMOS transistors and PMOS transistors. So
let's go ahead and start putting this together.
So one of the things we need to do is we need
to put in two switches. So I'm going to put a
second switch in. I'm going to and then I'm
going to put labels on those switches. So,
I'm going to say this switch is A. So, the top
switch is A. And then I press the label button
again. And then I say the bottom I select the
bottom switch. And that is B. And uh let's see
here. I'm going to I'm going to start over fresh.
Let me just delete let me delete the transistors
so we can sort of follow the diagram. So, we've
got an A and a B input. And then we're going to
to put two PMOS transistors at the top kind of
in parallel in series. So we just kind of connect
them end to end. And we'll just connect from the
in between them. We take the the S and the D and
we connect them in between. And so that's sort of
the top part of the circuit. So I might as well
connect the A input and the B input to these guys.
Okay. And then we have to put a couple of NMOS's.
Well, okay. We'll put a couple of end NMOS's here
and we'll put them sort of next to each other just
like in the diagram. Uh I I guess I should conduct
connect the the the positive voltage to the top
PMOS transistor. And then I am going to connect
just like in the picture. I'm going to connect the
bottom of the second PMOS transistor to the top
of the NOS transistors. But the output of these
NMOS transistors is supposed to be connected
together. And so we're going to have a common
output. And it and it turns out that when we put
our probe here, we can connect it to any any of
these connections because they're just one wire
basically. So they're all connected together.
And so that's our output. And then the next thing
we need to do is connect our input to both of the
NMOS transistors at the bottom. And you see it's
kind of toggling on and off. And then the last
thing we've got to do is we got to connect the
ground to the bottom of the NMOS transistors. So
at this point I think that I have replicated this
circuit on the right hand side. So let's take a
look at the specifications. We're supposed to add
a probe component and label it Q. So, we need to
go to the label button and put Q on as our label.
So, it that way the grader can grade it. Um,
connect the inputs. The A and B are the inputs.
Um, let's let's look at the truth table. And so,
right now we have A as zero and B is
zero. So, if we make them both zero,
then we should get a one as the output. So, A and
B are now both zero and Q is output of one. So now
if we turn any of these to one the output would
be zero. So A of one and B of zero is the output
of zero. A of one and B of one output is zero. And
uh let's see which one B of one outputB of one and
A of zero output of one. And so the only time the
output turns to one is when both A and B. And so
we have correctly built replicated the image that
we had from class and we have tested it. So now
let's see if the auto grader likes it. So let's
see what it does. So it first it looks to see if
we have A and B and Q labeled correctly. And then
it says we're going to go through. It looks like
it's going to go through all the truth tables.
Truth table. Truth table. Truth table. And we
have been successful. And let's save this before
we're done. This is a NOR. And so if we come back,
we could load this back up. So if you're fooling
around and you're building your own circuits,
um, and so you you can save things or if you're
working on it and you're not sure you got it right
and you want to go back and watch the lecture.
So, uh, I think that pretty much covers all
of the feature of our CMOS layout editor for
computer architecture for everybody. Cheers.